Today's דף daf is
דף ט"ו, daf Tes Vav, excuse me, ט"ז, Tes Zayin, 16, and
we pick up, we're a little behind, we pick up at the
bottom right before the משנה Mishnah of ט"ו עמוד ב' Tes Vav
Amud Bet and we just had like a key key discussion about
how to understand half damages for קרן, Keren, whether it's ממון mamon
that really you are negligent but the Torah's giving you like you're
so close to the line that the Torah is sort of saying
you only have to pay half, or whether it's קנס knas fundamentally
it's not negligent but you're so close to the line and the
Torah wants to if not punish, encourage a higher level of שמירה
shemirah and therefore it's קנס, knas, and although the evidence seemed to
point to ממון mamon the גמרא Gemara concludes that it's קנס knas
although we have a ברייתא baraita that says anytime you pay more
than damages you're paying קנס knas with the implication being if you're
paying less than full damages it's ממון. mamon. The גמרא Gemara says
no, sometimes ממון, mamon, sometimes קנס. knas. חצי נזק צרורות Chatzi Nezek
Tzerorot where the negligence is full it's just that the animal did
not directly damage but it was through the pebbles that it kicked,
there there's a הלכה halakhah of half and that's clearly ממון. mamon.
There's no reason it shouldn't be ממון, mamon, you're just somehow technically
not paying full because your animal didn't do it directly, whereas חצי
נזק Chatzi Nezek of קרן, Keren, that says the גמרא, Gemara, that
will be קנס. knas. So the conclusion is that it's קנס, knas,
and this is going to be have a lot of implications as
we continue to learn קרן, Keren, the most obvious one being what
the גמרא Gemara said earlier that if you admit that your animal
gored you don't pay because קנס knas you don't pay on your
own admission. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to draw though right
before the משנה Mishnah some other very relevant applications which is actually
going to tie in to the theme of the משנה, Mishnah, of
the coming up משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
דהשתא דאמרת פלגא ניזקא קנסא. de-hashta de-amart palga nizka knasa. Line starts
with the word ניזקא קנסא, nizka knasa, to about ten lines before
the משנה Mishnah on ט"ו עמוד ב'. Tes Vav Amud Bet. Now
that you've told me that half נזק, nezek, half-damages for קרן Keren
is a קנס, knas, האי כלבא דאכל אמרי, hai kalba de-achal imrei,
if you have a dog that ate sheep, ושונרא דאכל תרנגולא, ve-shunra
de-achal tarnigola,
or a cat that ate a chicken,
cats probably were a little bit less domesticated than the cats that
we're talking about, dogs probably also, anyway משונה הוא, meshuneh hu,
that's doing something unusual, out of the ordinary, ולא מגבינן בבבל, ve-lo
magbinan be-Bavel, and we don't collect it in בבל. Bavel. Now, meaning
because basically the basic חידוש chiddush here is sort of not stated
explicitly. The basic חידוש chiddush is that an animal that does something
that is seen as unexpected, משונה, meshuneh, is seen as a type
of a
קרן. Keren. Next משנה Mishnah is going to talk about a sheep
that eats דבר שאינו ראוי לה, davar she-eino ra'uy lah, something that's
not fit for it, like it goes ahead and it eats, it
eats clothes, it chews on somebody's shirt.
So there the משנה Mishnah says that you pay half damages. Now
so presumably when do you like what's the logic about that? So
that presumably you could go two ways: you could say maybe we're
doing sort of like by analogy, the same way there's an unusual
form of קרן Keren which is not expected which is the first
three times, there's an unusual form of שן ורגל, Shen ve-Regel, something
that you could not have anticipated and you pay half but it's
a type of a שן Shen and a type of a
רגל. Regel. Another way of thinking about it is anytime it does
something that it could not have been expected but it does damages
that automatically becomes a type of a קרן. Keren. What would be
the נפקא מינה nafkamina between that? Let's see who's paying attention. What's
the נפקא מינה nafkamina between if an animal does an eating that's
unusual, it chews on a shirt, whether you call that an unusual
שן Shen and because it's an unusual שן Shen you pay half
damages, or you call it a type of a קרן. Keren.
First of all, can it ever be a מועד? mu'ad? Because let's
say it does it three times,
it becomes a מועד mu'ad by שן. Shen. All right, but maybe
that's a good point, would we make the same analogy if we're
making an analogy to allow for a process of becoming a מועד?
mu'ad? That's a good point. But what's the most immediate נפקא מינה?
nafkamina?
Is it קנס knas or is it ממון mamon based on what
we just said?
All right, but maybe again by analogy we would say if there's
a תם tam by קרן, Keren, maybe there's a תם tam by
שן Shen and it also would be קנס. knas. No, but what's
the most immediate נפקא מינה? nafkamina? פטור ברשות הרבים! patur bi-reshut ha-rabim!
Exactly, if it's שן Shen you're פטור ברשות הרבים, patur bi-reshut ha-rabim,
if it's קרן Keren you're חייב ברשות הרבים. chayav bi-reshut ha-rabim. So
this is going to be a really interesting question because the next
משנה Mishnah is going to introduce and the following משניות Mishnayot that
an unusual type of a שן Shen pays half damages. And is
that a type of a שן Shen or is that a type
of a קרן? Keren? Now most ראשונים Rishonim assume that it is
a type of a
קרן. Keren. Why?
Well, because they are assuming that the חידוש, chiddush, it's sort of
like you were sort of saying. If the Torah is מחדש mechadesh
a category of קרן, Keren, if it's paying ממון, mamon, if it's
basically saying that look, when you're so close to the line you
don't pay full, there's like a rationale to that. So then we
should by analogy apply it to other categories, apply it to שן
Shen and רגל. Regel. קנס knas tends to be more arbitrary. Fines
are more arbitrary. So therefore what we're going to, a lot of
ראשונים Rishonim assume that once we decide half-damages is a קנס knas
by קרן... Keren... קרן Keren and we're going to say other types
of things also pay half, like a like an unusual type of
a שן, Shen, then the only way we sort of get that
to pay half is by calling it a type of a קרן
Keren because if if a fine is a חידוש Chiddush and if
you're going to make it apply by other things, you're going to
say that they really fall into the same category. And then what
we wind up saying is, and it's a very strange idea, that
קרן Keren is not just defined by כוונה להזיק. Kavana Lehazik. קרן,
Keren, something is a קרן Keren by the virtue of the fact
that it does an unusual type of a damage, an unexpected type
of way of damaging. And that's on its own makes something a
קרן. Keren. Okay, so that's like a key point here that we're
going to apply the idea of קרן Keren to other things. We're
going to say other things are also a קנס, Knas, but you
should just be aware that most ראשונים Rishonim assume what this גמרא
Gemara means is is that those other things also get called a
קרן Keren and are חייב Chayav in רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. But
there does always remain the possibility that no, actually maybe those other
things are שן Shen and רגל Regel and we're just applying by
analogy the same type of principle. Right, so that's just the the
most core question is, are we saying everything that's unusual is a
קרן Keren even if it's not כוונה להזיק, Kavana Lehazik, or are
we applying it by analogy? But now that we've established that half
damages are קנס, Knas, when it applies to a case like this,
like a dog that eats a sheep or a cat that eats
a chicken, משונה הוא ולא מגבינן בבבל. Meshuneh hu velo magbinan BeBavel.
Because it's משונה, Meshuneh, it's unusual and it's a קנס, Knas, we
don't collect in בבל. Bavel. In בבל Bavel we need, you know,
the ability to impose either physical punishments, lashes, death, or even to
impose fines is something that you need סמיכה Smicha from ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. You do not impose a קנס Knas in בבל. Bavel.
So number one is, we don't impose קנסות Knasos in בבל, Bavel,
and if we call this a קנס Knas we're not going to
impose it in בבל. Bavel. והני מילי ברברבי, Vehani mili beravrevei, that's
only if it eats like a big sheep or a big chicken.
אבל בזוטרי, Aval bezutrei, a small sheep, אורחיה הוא, Orcheih hu, that
would be normal. Okay. ואי תפס לא מפקינן מיניה. Ve-i tafas lo
mafkinan minei. Now, okay, it's very nice we don't collect it in
בבל, Bavel, what about the poor...
And he pays full damages or...
No it would be half. Again, half damages, קנס, Knas, and therefore
one implication is you don't collect it in בבל. Bavel. But now
we've got a problem, which is the poor person whose sheep was
eaten is out. He doesn't even get half damages. So ואי תפס
לא מפקינן מיניה. Ve-i tafas lo mafkinan minei. Ah, but if he
seizes the property from the person who damaged him, then we don't
go ahead and make him pay back. So in the end of
the day, we say he deserves compensation, at least half compensation. Okay,
so even though we don't judge דיני קנסות Dinei Knasos in בבל,
Bavel, we don't force the money out of him, out of to
take away from him if he grabbed it. That's a type of
a... Yeah, that's a good question. Can you sort of do it
with a wink and a nod? That's anyway a type of a
עבדינן דינא דנפשיה, Avdinan dina denafshei, especially here because we can't do
the דין, Din, he's doing it himself. He's not even circumventing the
court, I mean the courts aren't acting in this case. ואמר קבעו
לי זימנא דאזלינא לארץ ישראל. Ve-amar kive'u li zimna de-azlina Le-Eretz Yisrael.
If he goes to a court here in בבל Bavel and says,
you know, fix me a time that and I'm going to go
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and the the מזיק Mazik has to
come with me and we're going to go have the court case
heard in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, then קבינן ליה, Kavinan leh, then
we would put him on the court schedule and he'd be able
to force the מזיק Mazik to stand judgment in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Of course, at that stage he might want to just pay
him back so he doesn't have to שלעפ shlep over and do
the travel expense. ואי לא אזל, Ve-i lo azal, if the מזיק
Mazik doesn't want to go go to the court case in Israel,
משמתינן ליה, Meshamtinan leh, we put him in a נידוי. Nidui. ובין
כך ובין כך, Uvein kach uvein kach, and either way, whether, you
know, he asks to he's trying to bring the case to Israel
or not,
משמתינן ליה עד דמסלק היזיקא, Meshamtinan leh ad demassilek hezeika, we would
put a נידוי, Nidui, excuse me, on the מזיק Mazik until he
actually got rid of this dangerous animal. Because here this animal is
doing... well that's a question the ראשונים Rishonim ask. They say are
we talking even one time or not? So they debate that, what
exactly the parameters are. Okay, but here this animal is at... I
understand. Okay, but maybe the משונה Meshuneh is also a signal to
a violent nature. So, you know, it's a little two sides of
the coin. Okay, מדרבי נתן. Mid'Rabbi Natan. And this is a question
you were asking earlier, Michael, which is what responsibility do I have
to remove a animal that's dangerous? דתניא, Detanya, as a ברייתא, Braita,
רבי נתן אומר מניין שלא יגדל אדם כלב רע בתוך ביתו ואל
ימיד סולם רעוע בתוך ביתו. Rabbi Natan omer minayin shelo yigadel adam
kelev ra betoch beito ve'al yamid sulam rau'ah betoch beito. How do
you know not to have a a bad dog, like a what's
it called, a mad dog in your house, or a
a unstable ladder, rickety ladder? תלמוד לומר לא תשים דמים בביתך. Talmud
lomar lo tasim damim beveitecha. Do not allow blood to be in
your house fall in your house, meaning you cannot do anything that
creates danger for other people. So there's a whole discussion in the
ראשונים Rishonim that I don't want to get to, which is obviously
the correct question to ask, but anyway what exactly would be the
the what do you call it, the threshold that we would say
this animal is dangerous enough that you have to get rid of
it. תוספות Tosfos discusses maybe there are some animals that you can
tie up in a chain, other animals that are even more dangerous
that you have to actually get rid of. Okay, so that's a
discussion. More directly for our interests, I'd like to discuss this issue
about תפס
לא מפקינן מיניה. Tafas lo mafkinan minei.
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, very interesting תוספות,
Tosfos, little תוספות Tosfos here at the bottom. ואי תפס לא מפקינן
מיניה. Ve-i tafas lo mafkinan minei. תוספות Tosfos says, אמר רבינו תם,
Amar Rabbeinu Tam, דוקא אי תפס המזיק עצמו כגון כלב או שור.
Davka i tafas hamazik atzmo kegon kelev o shor.
No,
no, the animal that is the damaging animal, okay? דלא מפקינן מיניה.
delo mafkinan minei. ובמזיק הכי גוונא כגון פחלא לאחזוקי אומנותו בשעת
היזק. u'v'mazik hachi gavna kegon pachala l'achzuki umanuto b'sha'at hezek. That sets
up two questions to you. One question is how much if we
apply the idea of half damages by an act of eating and
we make it a type of a קרן keren or a שן
משונה, shein meshuneh, how much do we also say the idea that
you collect from the body of the animal, which is a little
implied in תוספות Tosfos although he doesn't say it explicitly? Okay, that's
סתם stam a question. Even if you went to בית דין, beis
din, how much would you pay cash half damages, how much would
you collect from the body of the animal? But the other point
תוספות Tosfos is bothered is is that if we're not דן דיני
קנסות dan dinei knasos in בבל, Bavel, people will just I'm just
gonna seize your Ferrari and I'm gonna say yeah because of a
קנס knas that you because you did something your animal whatever I'll
make up I'll say say some story about some קנס knas you
owe me and בית דין beis din won't be able to hear
the case. Well we can't hear that case because we don't דן
דיני קנסות dan dinei knasos in בבל Bavel so you might as
well just keep hold hold onto the Ferrari. So תוספות Tosfos says
wait wait that's not possible, like how can we allow such a
thing? Okay? He says אבל מידי אחריני לא דאי בכל דבר שתפס
לא מפקינן, aval midei achrinei lo d'ei be-chol davar she-tafas lo mafkinan,
if we basically say well we can't listen to the case so
we just let you keep what you grabbed, יבא לידי תקלה דהיום
ולמחר יטול כל אשר לו ולא נוציא דאין דנין דיני קנסות ויוציא
מחוטא מה שהזיק. yavo lidei takala de-hayom u'l'machar yitol kol asher lo
velo notzi de'ein danin dinei knasos ve-yotzi mi-chotei ma she-hizik.
So the most we can do is if we're gonna do a
hands-off approach is say if somebody claims that their animal was damaged,
okay, we'll let him seize the damaging animal. Now even there מקשים
תוספות makshin Tosfos do you have to like bring some evidence that
your animal was eaten? I mean I don't know if the animal's
all eaten maybe there's no evidence. So even there you could say
you could make up a story and at least seize the guy's
nice prize bull worth a million dollars. Okay, anyway that's תוספות's Tosfos
approach. תוספות's Tosfos approach is not דנין דיני קנסות danin dinei knasos
in בבל Bavel means we won't even listen to the case even
if a guy grabbed the property. A lot of ראשונים Rishonim disagree.
And a lot of ראשונים Rishonim say when I grab Michael's Ferrari
that does not start as a דין קנס. din knas. Prima facie
what that starts is is גזילה. gezeilah. Okay? Now I am claiming
it's not גזילה gezeilah because of some קנס knas he owes me.
בית דין beis din is going to listen to the case enough
to determine whether or not there was a damage or not a
damage. Is it גזילה? gezeilah? If it's there's no damage it's גזילה
gezeilah I give it back. If there was some damage then they'll
say okay then as far as we can tell because we'll do
an estimate of how much of the damage was, it seems like
actually that was equivalent to the damage and it's not גזילה gezeilah
or it's more than the damage and you have to give back
x amount. Okay, and but תוספות Tosfos is saying that is not
a lot of ראשונים Rishonim say that's not דנין דיני קנסות. danin
dinei knasos. At the end of the day we're going to have
to listen to the to the particulars, but because that's because we're
דנין דיני גזילה danin dinei gezeilah not דיני קנסות. dinei knasos. We're
listening to the particulars to determine whether or not it's גזילה. gezeilah.
Okay, so that's so that's how a lot of ראשונים Rishonim sort
of deal with that and it gets to very interesting discussions in
the ראשונים Rishonim about how much are בית דין's beis din hands
tied in בבל Bavel if they can't דן דיני קנסות dan dinei
knasos and if you allow some way of compensation by תפס, tafas,
how much then can we actually get involved in the case? And
this became an issue not just by goring oxen, but it became
an issue about personal damage. 'Cause when I do a personal damage
and I say some of the things I pay like pain and
suffering or whatever are also דיני קנסות. dinei knasos. And how much
are we saying that a person isn't entitled to collect those? So
it becomes a very interesting question about the way of somewhat restoring
a balance by this principle of like תפס, tafas, you know עביד
איניש דינא לנפשיה, avid inish dina l'nafshei, taking law into your own
hands, and then how much is בית דין beis din going to
at that stage get involved in a serious way? Yeah.
But I understand according to תוספות Tosfos that it's limited to the
body of the animal, over here it seems to be at the
end of the day רבי נתן Rabbi Natan you've I'm gonna put
a חרם cherem like get rid of the animal so I so
I take your animal it's damaging it but I gotta kill it
because it's a...
No, that's a good point. You'd have to sort of say that
the threshold of מסלקינן הנזק mesalkinan ha-nezek is high or maybe I'll
just שחט shacht it. Maybe it's a nice cow and I'll שחט
shacht it and get all the meat. But it's a... Yeah, okay,
you're right and maybe it there's different thresholds and maybe I can
tie it up with a chain. Yeah, you had a question?
I just wondered about the principle of
תפיסה לבעל חוב. tfisa l'baal chov. I mean is it is תוספות
Tosfos saying that in regards to assumption that the lien on the
animal the ממונא mamona or is that there's an actual תפיסה tfisa
in the animal? Once your animal takes my stuff I automatically own...
Right, so that's what I was saying. Because it's sort of built
on this קרן keren model then the רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam like
makes double sense. Number one is he's trying to limit the scope
of תפס. tafas. And number two is he might be building on
the assumption that because of קרן keren you actually do own a
part of the animal. Right, but the פשט pshat of the גמרא
Gemara is not limited to that. And even if I don't have
a lien in terms of if you sell your property to somebody
else, if you owe me the money I have a right to
any of any property that you own right now including you know
מטלטלין. metaltelin. Okay. All right. Yes.
Are they saying that there's no reason to say that the court
would
force the return of the property?
They would have looked at the case and if I seize more
than the קנס knas then I would have to return the property.
Yeah.
So basically saying there's no קרן keren now in בבל Bavel for
the...
Well no for the first three times. Right. So yeah, okay. The
interesting question is do you listen to the קבלת עדות kabbalas eidus
to turn it into a מועד muad to get it to the
point of being a מועד muad or is that also type of
דיני קנסות? dinei knasos? So this is obviously this tiny little גמרא
Gemara becomes the basis of a lot of... a lot of literature
of the ראשונים Rishonim about what power we have in בבל Bavel
to deal with these cases. But as I said also to me,
the bigger issue that I think we're going to be dealing with
in the next few דפים dappim is what's this idea of an-
an משונה שן? meshuneh shein? Is it a type of a שן
shein or a type of a קרן? keren? Let's take a look
at the next משנה. mishnah. חמישה תמימים וחמישה מועדים. chamisha tamim ve-chamisha
muadim. Five animals are תם tam and five are
מועד. muad. הבהמה אינה מועדת, habehemah einah muades, here's the five types
of תמים tamim there are. It's really all forms of קרן. keren.
לא ליגח lo ligach not to gore, ולא ליגוף velo ligof for
to push, ולא לישוך velo lishoch to bite, as opposed to to
eat, ולא לירבוץ velo lirvots to crouch on something presumably with the
intention of breaking it, ולא ליבוט velo livot or to kick. So
those are five types of קרן. keren. But anyway, those are- if
it does any of those, it's a תם. tam. Other types of
things it'll do, it's not קרן, keren, it's שן, shein, it's רגל,
regel, whatever it is, and it's מועד. muad. השן, hashein, now here's
the type of five מועדים, muadim, or this is presumably what it's
going to be saying. השן מועדת לאכול את הראוי לה. hashein muades
lechol es harauy lah. If an animal eats things that it- it's
normal for it to eat as opposed to chewing on clothes, then
it's
שן.
shein. It'll eat anything?
I mean, so for a goat it would be normal. Okay, each
animal would be judged on its own terms. But if it eats
normal things it's שן, shein, it's מועד. muad. The presumption being, what
if it eats not normal things? So again, the presumption is that
that's going to be a type of a תם שן, tam shein,
right? That's like the implication. A מועד שן muad shein is eating
normal things. A תם שן tam shein is eating abnormal things. It
sounds like, you know, but anyway, it's laying the groundwork for that
type of an idea. הרגל מועדת לשבור בדרך הילוכה. haregel muades lishbor
bederech hiluchah. The- the רגל, regel, you know, is מועד muad to
break things in its normal way of walking. Not clear if there
would be a תם tam version of that. Okay. ושור המועד, veshor
hamuad, now those are two מועדים. muadim. ושור המועד, veshor hamuad, a
שור shore that is מועד, muad, meaning that it was a תם
tam but it was warned three times, and now it's a מועד
muad for type of a קרן. keren. ושור המזיק ברשות הניזק, veshor
hamazik birshus hanizak, if let's say you do it ברשות הניזק, birshus
hanizak, remember we've discussed a few times now the position of רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon that a קרן keren in the רשות הניזק, reshus
hanizak, in the damagee's domain, pays full damages even from the outset.
So what makes it מועד? muad? You know, מועד muad is this
slippery term. מועד muad sometimes means it's habitual, and sometimes means the
law is that it pays full. Okay, here it means the law
is that it pays full. It's not more habitual to gore in
רשות הניזק, reshus hanizak, but it pays full. ואדם. ve-adam. Like now
does it mean- like when we say אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad
le-olam, whether awake or asleep or whatever. Presumably we're not saying that
it's habitual for a man to do damage, okay, I mean maybe
you could depending on if you're a Hobbesian or what your general
idea is about human nature. But what we're saying is whenever you
do damage you pay full. Okay, so those are the five types
of scenarios of full payment. Now of course what we're missing is
what about- what about אש? esh? What about בור? bor? But these
are about like living beings. Five types of מועד muad for living
beings.
Okay. Now, הזאב והארי והדוב והנמר והברדלס. haze'ev ha'ari vadov vehanamer vehabordelis.
A- a
fox- no, זאב ze'ev is a wolf, excuse me. A wolf, a
lion, a bear, hey my name is mentioned. Okay, a נמר namer
is what's a נמר, namer, a leopard? A- right? Leopard. And a
ברדלס bordelis which the גמרא gemara will discuss, but I think the
גמרא gemara seems to mean it's like a hyena or something of
that nature. והנחש. vehanachash. Yes,
and the נחש nachash and the snake. הרי אלו מועדים. harei elu
muadim. By the way, הזאב ארי דוב נמר ברדלס נחש haze'ev ari
dov namer bordelis nachash is six, so it doesn't fit the five
pattern. הרי אלו מועדים. harei elu muadim. Those are מועד muad from
the outset. Now, to do damage. Here's an interesting question. If your
lion goes ahead and attacks my sheep and eats my sheep and
it's a מועד, muad, okay, or whatever, you know, is that שן
shein or רגל, regel, or is that a שן shein or קרן?
keren? Presumably it's a שן, shein, right? And it's a type of
an eating, right? But
when you think about these things, these dangerous animals, and you have
this big flashing word 'dangerous' over them, you tend to more- more-
more think about like, oh my god, this is a type of
a קרן, keren, because you think קרן, keren, you know, you think
כוונה להזיק. kavanah le-hazik. And we tend to anthropomorphize, I think, and
sort of see sometimes, you know, the propensity and the- the sort
of violence engage- you know, with these types of things, especially because
they attack living beings, I think we tend to- we would tend
to naturally think of these as a type of a קרן. keren.
But how many of these things are trying to do it just
for the sake of causing damage? They're trying to do it for-
for their food. So, you know, it's like those nature- right, videos
in the wild, right? They should be rated sometimes like PG-13 because
of the violence, right? But it might be violent, but it's still
essentially a type of a שן, shein, and that's essentially what the
גמרא gemara is going to say, yes.
The distinction between expected and unexpected also. Right. I mean here it's
actually expected.
I understand, it's expected. But I'm just saying if you would ask
somebody what type category would you put when a lion attacks into
קרן keren or שן, shein, the most instinctive response is I think
קרן keren because of the degree of violence. Right? But when you
take a step back you realize one minute, it's just doing it
to eat, and it's a type of a שן. shein. So, either
way it's- so anyway, but the גמרא- gemara so the point is,
is that- is that- is that-
well we'll see in the גמרא. gemara. If it's קרן- keren the
גמרא gemara will assume basically it's שן. shein. And then what it's
really just saying, but if you just think about it, if that's
what it's saying then it's not such a חידוש, chiddush, right? Because
then it's basically saying well we already said a שן מועדת לאכול
את הראוי לה. shein muades lechol es harauy lah. So all you're
really telling me is for a lion, ראוי לו ra'uy lo are
sheep and ראוי לו ra'uy lo are, I don't know, are, you
know, are cows or whatever they are, but it's not really a
different category than a שם אורחא לאכול את הראוי לו. shem orcha
le-echol et ha-ra'uy lo. Okay, so it's interesting whether we're thinking about
this as שן shen or קרן. keren. Yeah.
I was just, not to jump, but
I think רש"י Rashi just fits what you just said. So רש"י
Rashi sort of says אפילו בנשיכה בכל נזיקין. afillu bi-neshikha be-khol nezikin.
Oh, that's a good point. You're right. Thank you for that. Right.
So רש"י Rashi says, thank you for that. Because I was actually
thinking תוספות Tosafot emphasizes the שן shen component, רמב"ם Rambam less so,
and you're right, רש"י Rashi does seem to be sort of also
אפילו בנשיכה בכל נזיקין. afillu bi-neshikha be-khol nezikin. Thank you. So once
you're dealing with a lion, presumably even if a lion does something
that is just destructive, right, you know, then it's also a type
of a קרן מועד. keren mu'ad. Right, so you're right. So thank
you. So תוספות Tosafot really tries to limit this into the שן
shen box and say other types of, you know, but you're right,
רש"י Rashi and רמב"ם Rambam also by somewhat by implication, רמבם Rambam
doesn't sort of limit certain types of eatings, he doesn't limit it
to רשות הניזק, reshut ha-nizak, you know, תוספות Tosafot limits it to
רשות הניזק reshut ha-nizak because תוספות Tosafot says if it's a שן
shen in רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabbim, yeah, your lion in the רשות
הרבים reshut ha-rabbim no problem, just don't bring him into my, anyway,
so that's the question. Dov, you had a question?
Well, it's just the two uses of territorial kinds of attacks by
animals. One is for food and one is just being territorial.
Oh, interesting. Aha.
So a violence without a purpose.
Aha. You mean because somebody like walks into its territory? I see.
And it just attacks. That's interesting. Yeah, it's like a bear. When
a bear feels threatened, right, that's the דב, dov, right? It's going
to attack. Right. When they tell people that are walking through the
woods and you hear bears and make a lot of noise, right,
it's exactly that. It's like animals who feel threatened and attack. So
that's an excellent, what? A fish. That's an excellent point. You're right.
So I wasn't, yeah, yeah, so you're right. So that actually reinforces
the idea that the חידוש chidush of the משנה mishnah is the
פשט pshat really is like רש"י Rashi and it is this idea
that really any type of violence is its nature, whether it's to
eat or not to eat,
and therefore it's a קרן מועד keren mu'ad to begin with.
Although you could say, I just want to interrupt, sorry, you could
say it's a רגל, regel, you don't have to say it's a
שן. shen. Meaning, here we have a nature that is its natural
nature to be territorial as you described it. It's not כוונה להזיק.
kavvannah le-hazik. Right, we tend to anthropomorphize and see it as like
oh it's just doing a meaningless act of violence. Right, it's like
it's כוונה להזיק. kavvannah le-hazik.
Right. Well, I guess like why anyway would an animal have כוונה
להזיק? kavvannah le-hazik? But anyway, but it is interesting. Like if it's
nature to be territorial and to protect its territory and to use
violence to do that, maybe it's a type of a קרן. keren.
Although you're right, כוונה להזיק kavvannah le-hazik doesn't have to mean because
of רשעות. rishus. It's intentionally trying to attack the human that goes
into its territory for the sake of protecting its territory. So anyway,
yeah, I would agree that I think the פשט pshat is, is
that this is saying that this is a קרן מועד keren mu'ad
to begin with. But תוספות Tosafot tries to put it all in
sort of the שן shen and רגל regel category and saying this
is just the animal's nature. It's sort of like the whole question
of like explaining away evil. Well, you know, it's just the nature,
so you can't, anyway, yeah.
To me this seems very interesting that, you know, sociologically people had
these kind of animals, you know, which is why they're talking about
it.
Yeah, that's right.
And then also how do you, you know, then if anything I
would think this would be the definition of כלב רע kelev ra
or whatever it is that רב נתן Rav Natan said.
Yeah, so the גמרא gemara is going to say that too. Like
you might have to kill these animals. But that's like a separate
conversation. Okay. Rabbi, yeah, did you...
I was also thinking about the מחלוקת machlokes about ממון mamon and
קנס kenas before and we were saying that according to ממון, mamon,
it's some, we were saying that it's like הלכות השימור. hilkhot ha-shimur.
Right,
this is kind of like הלכות השימור. hilkhot ha-shimur. Exactly. Right. Which
is although we are not, so really you should be חייב chayav
and by the שור, shor, but we don't make you חייב chayav
because it's not yet a מועד. mu'ad.
Right. But these start their lives as a קרן מועד, keren mu'ad,
which is exactly right. I think you're completely correct. I was reading
it too much through תוספות's Tosafot's lens. The פשט pshat is, they
absolutely that they start as a קרן מועד. keren mu'ad. And I
think that this point of כוונה להזיק, kavvannah le-hazik, that even though
they're doing it for good natural reasons, they're still you know sort
of consciously doing acts of damage, and so it really is a
קרן מועד. keren mu'ad. Yeah.
On this point, the Romans had circuses and
had these things.
Gladiator kind of things. Right. How much were they owned by private
people? It's an interesting question. Okay. I mean nowadays people own snakes.
People have all business. Oh, interesting.
Right, okay. Right, there's got to be money to be made. Okay.
Right.
These animals they train to people...
Right, right, right. רבי אליעזר אומר בזמן שהם בני תרבות אינם מועדין.
Rabbi Eliezer omer bi-zeman she-hem benei tarbus einam mu'adin. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer has a optimistic view. He thinks that these animals can be
domesticated. So if you've got, maybe this is it, like a trained,
you know, circus lion, then it's not a מועד. mu'ad. Okay. So
you can sort of reverse the process. Normally animals which do כוונה
להזיק kavvannah le-hazik start as תם tam and become מועד. mu'ad. This
animal can start as a מועד mu'ad and can become תם. tam.
Okay, you can domesticate it.
Isn't like Siegfried and Roy and all those years he got
like eaten by one of his lions? I know. ונחש מועד לעולם.
ve-nahash mu'ad le-olam. But a snake can never be domesticated, okay? Does
this have
certain religious metaphysical connotations with the whole symbolism of the snake, or
is it just no, like some assessment that these other animals, I
don't know, like if you ask me, I don't think you can
domesticate a lion or a bear any more than you can a
snake. But okay. Snake charmers. Yeah, they do have snake charmers, that's
true.
Snake charmers are weird.
Alright, okay, okay. חברה, chevre, we're moving forward. מדקתני, midkatani, השן מועדת
לאכול את הראוי לה, hashin muadet leechol et harauy lah, מכלל, mikhlal,
גמרא, Gemara, דבחצר הניזק
עסקינן. debechatzer hanizak askinan. If it says the שן shein has a
propensity to damage things that it's natural, it normally eats, then we're
talking in the in the in the yard of the הניזק. hanizak.
וקתני בהמה אינה מועדת לשלם. vekatani behema eina muadet leshalem. And then
it also says that a normal קרן keren does not pay full,
right? A normal קרן keren doesn't pay full, a normal שן shein
does pay full. But if we're talking in the same zone, right,
in the חצר הניזק, chatzer hanizak, why is a קרן keren not
paying full? The later in the Mishnah it says that בחצר הניזק
bechatzer hanizak קרן keren pays full. Okay, so it says אינה מועדת
לשלם כולה אבל חצי נזק משלמת, eina muadet leshalem kulah aval chatzi
nezek meshalemet, but it would pay half if it did it in
חצר הניזק. chatzer hanizak. מאני, mani, who is that? רבנן היא. Rabbanan
hi. דאמרי, de'amri, the Rabbis that say משונה קרן בחצר הניזק חצי
נזק הוא דמשלם. meshune keren bechatzer hanizak chatzi nezek hu demeshalem. When
something is unusual and it's a type of a קרן keren in
the חצר הניזק, chatzer hanizak, it still only pays half. Okay, so
presumably we're talking all in the same zone in the רשות הניזק.
reshut hanizak. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of
the Mishnah. שור המועד ושור המזיק ברשות הניזק והאדם. shor hamuad veshor
hamazik bereshut hanizak veha'adam. The things that it lists as מועד מתחילה
muad mitchila are a שור מועד, shor muad, three times warned, and
a שור המזיק ברשות הניזק, shor hamazik bereshut hanizak, a קרן keren
in the domain of the הניזק, hanizak, and a person. So here
it says a קרן keren in the domain of the הניזק hanizak
pays
full. אתאן לרבי טרפון. atan leRabbi Tarfon. So the end of the
Mishnah goes like Rabbi Tarfon דאמר משונה קרן בחצר הניזק נזק שלם
הוא דמשלם. de'amar meshune keren bechatzer hanizak nezek shalem hu demeshalem. That
when it's a קרן keren in the חצר הניזק chatzer hanizak it
pays full. רישא רבנן וסיפא רבי טרפון? reisha Rabbanan veseifa Rabbi Tarfon?
Is the beginning the Rabbis and the end Rabbi Tarfon? So again,
I would think the simplest thing to say is when the beginning
says that a קרן keren is תם, tam, it means in the
domain, you know, in the in the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. But
again, the Gemara is insisting that we say that everything is talking
in the same type of domain because otherwise you can't be comparing
them. So then it's not true, it wouldn't be תם tam according
to Rabbi Tarfon. So the Gemara says אין, in, yes, the Mishnah
is broken up into two
halves. דאמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה שיננא שבק מתניתין, de'amar lei Shmuel
leRav Yehuda shinena shevok matnitin, forget about the
Mishnah, ותא בתראי, veta batray, just listen to me. רישא רבנן וסיפא
רבי טרפון. reisha Rabbanan veseifa Rabbi Tarfon. Okay, which is obviously always
a hard answer but even more so here where it's clearly contrasting
five תמס tams to five מועדס. muads. רבי אלעזר משמיה דרב אמר,
Rabbi Elazar mishmeih deRav amar, now we're going to give other answers.
רבי אלעזר משמיה דרב אמר כולה רבי טרפון
היא. Rabbi Elazar mishmeih deRav amar
kuleih Rabbi Tarfon hi.
It's all Rabbi Tarfon. Okay, so רישא, reisha, now how is it
going to be that in the first case you're only going to
pay half damages if it's חצר הניזק chatzer hanizak if you pay
full by שן? shein? רישא בחצר המיוחדת לפירות לאחד ולזה ולזה לשורים.
reisha bechatzer hameyuchedet lepeirot le'echad ulezeh ulezeh leshorim.
Oh, you might remember this from yesterday, we had so much fun
with it. Anyway, a whole debate of Rashi Tosafot what the גרסא
girsa here is. I'll read it like Rashi though.
Okay, each owner has the right to bring their ox in, so
if it does an act of קרן, keren, it's a רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim because I had the right to have my ox there,
you had the right to have your ox there, it's like a
רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. So it does an act of קרן, keren,
it's רשות הרבים reshut harabbim pay half. But only you had the
right to have your fruit there, I didn't. So from the perspective
of the fruit, it's only your domain. And when my animal eats
your fruit, it's going to pay full. So that's a way we
would be talking about one domain where it pays it's חצר הניזק
chatzer hanizak for שן shein and it pays full because only you
have the right for your fruit, but it's רשות הרבים reshut harabbim
for קרן keren and you pay half because we both have the
right for our oxen. Okay? ולגבי שן הויא לה חצר הניזק ולגבי
קרן הויא לה רשות הרבים. ulegabei shein hava leh chatzer hanizak ulegabei
keren hava leh reshut harabbim. Okay,
just to point out again what I pointed out yesterday is that
the funny thing about this is that we could have a case
where I have a right to bring my ox there and I'm
going to be חייב chayav if it does an eating which is
natural to it. Okay, but that's at least Tosafot reads the Gemara
has a different גרסא girsa of the Gemara, but that's the way
Rashi reads it. אמר רב כהנא. amar Rav Kahana. So that anyway,
one way of getting out of it is let's not get overly
worried about which רשות reshut we're talking about, let's find a רשות
reshut in which they can all we can all be talking about
the same case. Okay, אמר רב כהנא אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד
מנהרדעא. amar Rav Kahana amritah leshmatta kammai deRav Zebid miNeharde'a. I said
over this discussion to Rav Zebid from Neharde'a. ואמר לי מי מצית
מוקמת לה כולה כרבי טרפון? ve'amar li mi matzit mokmat lah kuleih
keRabbi Tarfon? How can you read it like that, come up with
some רשות reshut so that we're talking about it's a חצר הניזק
chatzer hanizak for שן shein and רשות הרבים reshut harabbim for קרן
keren and it's all Rabbi Tarfon? מי מצית מוקמת לה כולה כרבי
טרפון? mi matzit mokmat lah kuleih keRabbi Tarfon? הא קתני השן מועדת
לאכול את הראוי לה. ha katani hashin muadet leechol et harauy lah.
We say that the שן'ס shein's liability is only when it eats
things that are natural for it. That's when it has full liability.
ראוי לה אין שאין ראוי לה לא. rauy lah in she'ein rauy
lah lo. Only when it's natural. ואי רבי טרפון האמר משונה קרן
בחצר הניזק נזק שלם הוא דמשלם. ve'ei Rabbi Tarfon ha'amar meshune keren
bechatzer hanizak nezek shalem hu demeshalem. This is a really good question.
He says, where is the שן shein doing the eating? When is
the שן shein doing the eating? When is שן חייב shen chayav
when it eats where?
In רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. Okay, now, let's say the שן shen
ate something unusual, it ate clothes, okay, so the משנה mishnah is
implying it wouldn't pay full. It's only paid full when it eats
food. It eats clothes, it's—but say wait one minute! But if it's
eating clothes and it's paying half, that turns it into a type
of a קרן. keren. But רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says that קרן
keren in רשות הניזק reshut hanizak pays full. So whether you call
it a שן shen and whether it's eating a natural thing and
it's a שן shen or an unnatural thing and it's a קרן,
keren, if it's all רשות הניזק reshut hanizak it should be paying
full. Okay,
very good. So the גמרא Gemara says, so it can't be רבי
טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. אלא לעולם רבנן היא, Ella le'olam rabanan hi,
the whole thing is רבנן. rabanan. So if the whole thing is
רבנן, rabanan, we have to deal with the line in the משנה
mishnah that says שור המזיק ברשות הניזק. shor hamazik breshut hanizak. That
line seems to be saying that קרן keren in רשות הניזק reshut
hanizak pays full. But we're saying the whole thing is רבנן. rabanan.
So אלא לעולם רבנן היא וחסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, Ella le'olam rabanan
hi vechasurei mechasra vehachi katani,
you've got to stick in some words. חמישה תמים הם, Chamisha tamim
hem, there are five תמים. tamim. ואם הועדו חמישתן מועדין. Ve'im hu'adu
chamishtan mu'adin.
So we're going to do a radical rewrite of the משנה. mishnah.
Five תמים tamim and five מועדים. mu'adim. You know what the five
מועדים mu'adim are? Not the things we mentioned, שן, shen, רגל, regel,
the five מועדים mu'adim are these five תמים tamim if they did
it three times. Then they're all מועד. mu'ad. Okay. So then I
don't know what the רש"י Rashi says. So then the rest of
the משנה mishnah is just telling you, oh by the way, here
are some other מועדים. mu'adim. Okay.
It's not really five מועדים. mu'adim.
Yeah, whatever, it's one
מועד, mu'ad, well
whatever, that's
true too. חמישה תמים הם ואם הועדו חמישתן חמישתן מועדים. Chamisha tamim
hem ve'im hu'adu chamishtan chamishtan mu'adin. ושן ורגל מועדים מתחילתן. Veshen varegel
mu'adin mitchilatan.
שן Shen and רגל regel are מועד mu'ad from the outset. And
now the hard phrase we have to deal with is שור המזיק
ברשות הניזק. shor hamazik breshut hanizak. That doesn't work for the רבנן.
rabanan. That seems like you pay full when it's a שן—when shen
it's a קרן ברשות הניזק. keren breshut hanizak So here's how we're
going to read it.
ושן ורגל מועדים מתחילתן. Veshen varegel mu'adin mitchilatan. והיכן העדתן בחצר הניזק.
Veheichan ha'adatan bechatzer hanizak. So when it says, okay, why am I
always... חמישה
תמים,
chamisha
tamim,
okay, וגו' לישוך v'go lishoch etc.
חמישה מועדים, chamisha mu'adim,
okay,
now we are saying what that means is the same thing, you
know, plus האדם ha'adam if it did it three times. Okay. We're
reading not as a new thing. Before we had, and then it
says שן, shen, רגל, regel, שור המועד, shor hamu'ad, שור
המזיק
ברשות הניזק,
shor hamazik
breshut
hanizak, and האדם. ha'adam. So we thought these
were the five מועדים, mu'adim, right? And he says no, no, no.
These are the five מועדים, mu'adim, the same thing. This is another
part of a משנה. mishnah. Okay. שן, Shen, רגל regel are מועד.
mu'ad. Where do they become a מועד, mu'ad, שור המועד, shor hamu'ad,
when are שן shen and רגל regel considered to be a מועד?
mu'ad? When they are being מזיק ברשות הניזק. mazik breshut hanizak. So
all of this becomes a commentary on, oh by the way, שן,
shen, רגל regel are מועד mu'ad when
it's רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. Okay, and אדם. adam.
So it's only... where'd the שור המועד shor hamu'ad get in there?
The שן shen and רגל regel are considered to be מועדים—oh—when mu'adim
they damage ברשות הניזק. breshut hanizak. Pretty, pretty bad read of the
משנה. mishnah. Okay, anyway. והיכן העדתן בחצר הניזק. Veheichan ha'adatan bechatzer hanizak.
מתקיף לה רבינא, Matkif lah Ravina, רבינא Ravina asked on this, הא
קתני לקמן, ha katani lekaman,
one minute, you can't say that's how you read the phrase שור
המזיק ברשות הניזק. shor hamazik breshut hanizak. A later משנה mishnah explains
what that phrase means. A later משנה mishnah says שור המזיק ברשות
הניזק כיצד, shor hamazik breshut hanizak keitzad,
and you know what it says? It says רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
says that if it does קרן ברשות הניזק keren breshut hanizak it's
full damages and the רבנן rabanan say it's half. So a later
משנה mishnah explicitly says that this phrase is קרן ברשות הניזק keren
breshut hanizak, and a debate of רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and the
רבנן. rabanan. Okay, so we're back to our problem that it sounds
like this is going like רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. And we pointed—showed
that the משנה mishnah couldn't be רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. אי אמרת
בשלמא איירי בה, Ei amrat bishlama ayiri bah, if this שור המזיק
shor hamazik is talking about קרן ברשות הניזק, keren breshut hanizak, משום
הכי קתני כיצד, mishum hachi katani keitzad,
so that's why a later משנה mishnah elabor—explains what it's about. אלא
אי אמרת לא איירי בה, Ella ei amrat lo ayiri bah, if
שור המזיק shor hamazik meant something completely different here, it did not
mean קרן ברשות הניזק, keren breshut hanizak? מאי כיצד, mai keitzad, how
could a later משנה mishnah be saying כיצד keitzad and describing it
as קרן ברשות הניזק? keren breshut hanizak. A later משנה mishnah makes
it clear. A later משנה mishnah introduces רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and
רבנן. rabanan. Okay, so a later משנה mishnah says, and a later
משנה mishnah says כיצד, keitzad, and it says רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
says full and רבנן rabanan say half. Okay, this is קרן, keren
קרן keren, ברשות הניזק. breshut hanizak. That's a later משנה. mishnah. So
the later משנה mishnah makes it clear that we're talking about that,
and therefore if we're counting it here as a מועד, mu'ad, we're
back to it being רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. But we pointed out
that the משנה mishnah can't be... Rabbi Tarfon. Okay, so אלא אמר
רבינא חסורי מחסרא והכי תני *Ella Amar Ravina Chasurei Mechasra Vehachi Tani*.
Let's try again. חמישה תמים הם ואם הועדו חמישה מועדים *Chamisha Tamim
Heim Ve'im Hu'adu Chamisha Muadim*. Like you said, the five and the
five are just the same five if they were if they were
warned. ושן ורגל מועדים מתחילתן *VeShein VeRegel Muadim Mitechilatan*. And now a
second part of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. שן shen ורגל *Shein VeRegel*
are מועד muad *Muad*. וזהו שור המועד *Vezehu Shor Hamuad*. Okay, so
שן shen ורגל *Shein VeRegel* are a type of that's the case
of a שור המועד *Shor Hamuad*, a שור *Shor* that starts its
life as a מועד muad *Muad* when it does שן Shen ורגל
*Shein VeRegel*. Now how do you do שור המזיק *Shor Hamazik*? If
that's saying it's מועד muad *Muad*, it's רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* and
we said it can't be רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*. So then it's
saying ושור המזיק ברשות הניזק bi-reshut ha-nizak. קרן Keren ברשות הניזק *VeShor
Hamazik Birshut Hanizak Keren Birshut Hanizak*. That's מחלוקת רבי טרפון ורבנן machloket
Rabbi Tarfon ve-Rabbanan, *Machloket Rabbi Tarfon VeRabbanan*. That's not a מועד muad.
*Muad*. We're saying okay, these are מועדים *Muadim*. We're saying here one
way of מועד muad *Muad* is that you made warned three times.
Another way of מועד muad *Muad* is שן Shen ורגל *Shein VeRegel*.
That's a type of a מועד muad *Muad*. שור המזיק ברשות הניזק
shor ha-mazik bi-reshut ha-nizak, *Shor Hamazik Birshut Hanizak* is a debate if
that's a מועד *Muad*. I even said it's a debate. I know,
that's what the later משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is going to say. But
say now we're just dealing with things, some are מועד *Muad*, some
are
debates of מועד *Muad*. אדם adam *Adam* is a מועד *Muad* and
זאב ארי דוב ברדלס bardelas? ונמר *Zeev Ari Dov Bardelas VeNamer* or
whatever... ברדלס ונמר *Bardelas VeNamer* is also a מועד *Muad*. So we're
just the way we're getting out of this being רבי טרפון *Rabbi
Tarfon* is reading it as rather than making an absolute statement that
this is a מועד *Muad*, we're saying this is a relevant category
which is actually a matter of debate.
I even said it's a debate.
I understand that.
And it's the only one that's a debate as opposed to all
the others.
I understand that. Okay. ויש מועדים אחרים כיוצא באלו *Veyesh Muadim Acherim
Kayotzei Beeilu*. And by the way, there's other מועדים *Muadim*. Number one,
אדם *Adam*, which we didn't mention, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* brings it in,
and זאב וארי דוב וברדלס ונמר ונחש *Zeev Ve'ari Dov VeBardelas VeNamer
VeNachash*. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya Nami Hachi*. So anyway, we have no
good read of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. This seems to be the
one the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is most happy with. And then we
have a ברייתא beraita *Braita* that seems to support it. חמישה תמים
הם ואם הועדו חמישה מועדים *Chamisha Tamim Heim Ve'im Hu'adu Chamisha Muadim*.
There are five תמים *Tamim* and if they were they warned they
all became מועד *Muad*. ושן ורגל מועדים מתחילתן *VeShein VeRegel Muadim Mitechilatan*.
And שן Shen. *Shein* and רגל regel *Regel* start their lives as
being a מועד *Muad*. וזהו שור המועד *Vezehu Shor Hamuad*. And that's
the case of of the way in which an ox is מועד
*Muad* from the beginning. ושור המזיק ברשות הניזק *VeShor Hamazik Birshut Hanizak*.
About the case about a קרן Keren *Keren* in רשות הניזק *Reshut
Hanizak*. That's מחלוקת רבי טרפון ורבנן *Machloket Rabbi Tarfon VeRabbanan*. That's a
debate of רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* and the רבנן *Rabbanan*. ויש מועדים
אחרים כיוצא באלו *Veyesh Muadim Acherim Kayotzei Beeilu*. There are other מועדים
*Muadim*. הזאב והארי Ha-ze'ev ve-ha-ari והדוב והנמר והברדלס והנחש *Hazeev Veha'ari Vehadov
Vehanamer Vehabardelas Vehanachash*.
Okay, so anyway a ברייתא beraita *Braita* that exactly says what we
just said before and that reads this משנה Mishna *Mishnah* in a
force of words, מחלוקת רבי טרפון ורבנן *Machloket Rabbi Tarfon VeRabbanan*.
Because it's the ברייתא braita *Braita* you mean. Even though it's exactly
what we said before, right. But I do have to say a
point that scholars have pointed out, which is sometimes you get a
case like this where the where there are ברייתות *Braitot* that are
only found in the בבלי *Bavli*, have no parallel in the ירושלמי
*Yerushalmi*, any other תנאיתי *Tannaitic* literature and they actually and and those
and and what happens is an אמורא *Amora* says a statement and
then you have a תניא נמי הכי *Tanya Nami Hachi* which is
word for word the same statement of the אמורא *Amora*. And the
this is the only evidence that such a ברייתא braita. *Braita* exists.
So presumably what we're not suggesting that they fabricated it, but presumably
you know if you pay as I pointed out before, if you
pay close attention, the language the אמוראים *Amoraim* speak is not is
not Aramaic. Meaning the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks Aramaic. The אמוראים *Amoraim*
when they give their מימרות *Memrot* speak in Hebrew, the same language
as the ברייתות *Braitot*. So it is possible that sometimes ברייתות *Braitot*
were actually statements of אמוראים *Amoraim* that became you know that became
understood to become ברייתות *Braitot*, you know what they do they were
just remembered as these teachings anonymous and they were believed to be
ברייתות *Braitot*. But it's very you know interesting. No, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* thinks it means we have a supporting ברייתא braita *Braita*. But
scholars say oh isn't this interesting. You have a supporting ברייתא Braita:
*Braita* that says word for word what you just said, which is
this very דחוק *Dachuk* explanation. And you didn't quote the ברייתא Braita,
*Braita* to begin with to prove it's what the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
meant. It only came up at the end after a whole discussion
and this ברייתא *Braita* has no parallels anywhere else. Right. So again
if you're sort of so if you're being cynical you say well
they made it up, but if you're being less cynical what you
say is is that this maybe the same teaching was remembered without
the אמורא *Amora*'s name and got to be remembered as a ברייתא
*Braita*, you know even if maybe it started as an אמוראית *Amoraitic*
statement. All right anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
This is really proving yourself by yourself.
Exactly.
That happens a lot. You know you you you you know you
take an assumption, you read it into the text and then you
prove what you're saying based on what the text just said. Okay.
איכא דרמי ליה מירמי *Ika Derami Lei Mirmi*.
Yes.
What?
ברייתא *Braita* is תנאיתי *Tannaitic*. But the question that's being raised is,
is this genuinely a תנאיתי *Tannaitic* source or believed to be תנאיתי
*Tannaitic* source. איכא דרמי ליה מירמי *Ika Derami Lei Mirmi*. Some show
a contradiction. תנן Tenan *Tenan*. חמישה תמים וחמישה מועדים *Chamisha Tamim VeHamisha
Muadim*. ותו ליכא *Vetuh Leika*? It's only five? How about the end
of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*? ואיכא זאב ארי דוב ונמר וברדלס ונחש
*Veika Zeev Ari Dov VeNamer VeBardelas VeNachash*. So they use the משנה
Mishna *Mishnah* itself to try to create this pressure to say the
משנה *Mishnah* can't just be read this simple way you read it.
ומשני U-meshani אמר רבינא חסורי מחסרא והכי תני חמישה תמים הם ואם
הועדו חמישה מועדים *Umeshani Amar Ravina Chasurei Mechasra Vehachi Tani Chamisha Tamim
Heim Ve'im Hu'adu Chamisha Muadim*. They're no no no the five is
just the five paralleling the first five. And then we move on
to a second stage in the משנה *Mishnah* talking about other מועדים
*Muadim*.
Okay. ושן ורגל מועדים מתחילתן וזהו שור המועד *VeShein VeRegel Muadim Mitechilatan
Vezehu Shor Hamuad*. ושור המזיק ברשות הניזק, the case of שור המזיק
ברשות הניזק, that's a מועד discussion, מחלוקת רבי טרפון ורבנן, ויש מועדין
אחרים כיוצא באלו הזאב והארי דוב ונמר וברדלס ונחש. ve-yesh muadin acherim
ke-yotzei be-elu ha-ze'ev ve-ha-ari dov ve-namer ve-bardelas ve-nachash. Okay fine. Good. We
got through that. Now moving on. What are back to the תם
tam stage? What are an animal תם tam for? Not to crouch
and intentionally like break things with an awareness that it's breaking it.
Okay. ולא לירבוץ. ve-lo lirvot. אמר אלעזר Amar Elazar לא שנו אלא
פחים גדולים אבל פחים קטנים אורחיהו. lo shanu ela pachim gedolim aval
pachim ktanim orcheihu.
So a lot of us know פחים קטנים pachim ktanim from the
famous מדרש midrash by יעקב, Yaakov, but anyway, here you have it
in a halakhic context. When is it not its way to destroy
like you know like like pots or whatever you know vessels by
sitting on it, pottery right, pots maybe makes you think about metal,
anyway, but when it's like a big one, like it doesn't crouch
on a big type of a vase or something. But a tiny
little one, you know, you know you ever go to the museum
and you see these like tiny little things that are used for
like having like you know perfume or other right they're tiny little
thing I mean you know maybe it's just sitting down and it
broke it. Okay. Or stepped on it I mean if stepped on
it would be certainly. לימא מסייע ליה. Leima mesayeia lei. Let's try
to bring a proof to this. הבהמה מועדת להלך כדרכה ולשבר ha-behema
muadet le-halech ke-darka u-le-shaber we have a ברייתא הבהמה ha-behema breaks things
in its natural way of walking ולשבר ולמעוך u-le-shaber u-le-ma'och and to
break
things ולמעוך את האדם ואת הבהמה ואת הכלים u-le-ma'och et ha-adam ve-et
ha-behema ve-et ha-kelim or vessels.
So you see there are ways in which it is מועד to
break vessels.
I mean is it really assumed to crush people?
Oh we're going to see. Okay so we'll get to that. So
anyway all right I understand, I understand, well right, okay, anyway, well
no רגל regel would be ברשות הניזק. But anyway the point is
that we got vessels, okay, so and before we said vessels it's
not, so I would have said that there is this is stepping
on it or crouching on it, but let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. So—so but the גמרא Gemara presumes so no the answer
is a big vessel versus a small one, a—a small one is
דרכו, darko, a big one is לא דרכו. lo darko. ומשני gives
a different answer. דילמא מן הצד. dilma min ha-tzad. No crushing means
when it catches like a person between a wall and it's walking
up against the wall right it's could that's how it could be
crushed. Like a pillow. Right exactly, that's how it could be crushing
a person. So also if like I don't know what the case
would be I don't know you got some vessel on a protrusion
and it's you know it's walking against it and the side of
its body is—is bumping against it, that would be כדרכו ke-darko whereas
to crouch on it would be שלא כדרכו. she-lo ke-darko. Again I
don't know why the גמרא Gemara doesn't make a difference to step
on it versus to crouch on it but either way the difference
is not big or small it's whether it's its normal way of
walking or if it's an act of—of crouching. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says איכא דאמרי ika de-amri some others say אמר אלעזר amar
Elazar לא תימא פחים גדולים הוא דלאו אורחיה lo teima pachim gedolim
hu de-lav orcheih don't just say big vessels is not the normal
way אבל פחים קטנים אורחיה aval pachim ktanim orcheih and small ones
would be normal אלא אפילו פחים קטנים נמי לאו אורחיה ela afilu
pachim ktanim nami lav orcheih even small ones would not be its
normal now to crouch on it presumably. Okay. מיתיבי Meitivei argue ולמעוך
את האדם ואת הבהמה ואת הכלים u-le-ma'och et ha-adam ve-et ha-behema ve-et
ha-kelim a ברייתא says it is natural for it to crush vessels.
אמר אלעזר Amar Elazar no דילמא מן הצד dilma min ha-tzad that
doesn't mean small vessels that means just when it's doing it with
the side of its body. Okay. איכא דרמי ליה מירמא ika de-rami
lei mirma it's just different ways of doing the same thing. Some
start this by showing a contradiction. תנן ולא לירבוץ ve-lo lirvotz is
that it's not מועד to crouch. והתניא Ve-hatanya ולמעוך את האדם ואת
הבהמה ואת הכלים u-le-ma'och et ha-adam ve-et ha-behema ve-et ha-kelim it does
say it is natural for it to break things as it's walking.
אמר אלעזר Amar Elazar לא קשיא lo kashya כאן בפחים גדולים כאן
בפחים קטנים kan be-pachim gedolim kan be-pachim ktanim big or small. Now
רש"י Rashi at one of these stages says if you're making the
difference between big or small, so if the case of crushing vessels
is only small vessels, what do you talk about אדם and בהמה?
behema? So רש"י Rashi. would say well it'd have to be a
little baby or it'd have to be a little baby בהמה behema
something. But I personally don't understand why it's—it's going to crushing with
its like body מן הצד min ha-tzad to me the natural difference
would be if there's a small vessel on the ground, maybe the
presumption is an animal will see a small vessel and not step
on it. But to me isn't there—why doesn't it difference between walking
stepping on something as opposed to crouching on something? The classic רגל
Regel. is stepping on something. Again I don't know animals maybe the
animal will be smart enough to avoid stepping on something. It probably
will be you know what your body crushes you're not afraid it's
going to throw you off balance, what you step on, you know
like animals are very sure-footed. I told you that story about that
when I was once horseback riding and we saw these like buggy
you know these people on these like you know you know also
like in the same area on these very you know big buggies
like these like very macho things or whatever so I was saying
to the person to one of people who was horseback riding with
me oh wouldn't that be cool I'd love to go in one
of those and she said no I would never I would never
want to ride in a buggy instead—instead you know over—over a horse.
I said what? Why not? She says well a buggy can go
over a—a cliff a horse will never go over a cliff. So
it's like okay. So anyway so animals maybe don't step on things
but you know they'll step on fruit cause they'll just smoosh the
fruit but they won't step on something hard you know they're smart
maybe they're smart enough not to step on it. But anyway I
wonder why the גמרא Gemara doesn't give the example of stepping on
something on—on stepping on something. All right.
But those buggies drawn by horses or?
No no no no no no I meant like those motorized yeah
anyway you know those like those macho things that go over the
sand dunes right anyway okay. הזאב והארי so the גמרא Gemara says
מאי ברדלס mai bardelas what is this ברדלס? So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי בורדלס? mai bordeles? What is this בורדלס? bordeles? Which is
like אמר רב יהודה נפרזא. amar Rav Yehuda Nafreza. That helps. מאי
נפרזא? mai nafreza? אמר רב יוסף אפא, amar Rav Yosef Apa, which
presumably is like a hyena or something. מתיבי. meitvei. רבי מאיר אומר
אף צבוע, Rabi Meir omer af tzavoa, even
a צבוע. tzavoa. רבי אליעזר אומר אף נחש, Rabi Eliezer omer af
nachash, even a snake. ואמר רב יוסף צבוע זו אפא, ve’amar Rav
Yosef tzavoa zu apa, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef says that a
צבוע tzavoa is an אפא. apa. So how could רב יוסף Rav
Yosef say a צבוע tzavoa is an אפא apa if
here רבי מאיר Rabi Meir meant what is a hyena if it's
already in the משנה as a בורדלס? bordeles? So then why would
רבי מאיר Rabi Meir have to add the hyena if the משנה
is talking about the hyena?
So it could be a polecat or a weasel.
Polecat or a weasel? Okay, I
trust Soncino.
Everything says a viper or something. It says cheetah.
A cheetah, right. Right, that's more like what Soncino was saying, a
cheetah or a hyena. Okay, so although a cheetah is a cat
and a hyena is a type of a dog, right? But anyway,
sort of think of them as more similar. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: Okay, לא קשיא כאן בצבוע זכר כאן בצבוע
נקבה. lo kashya kan betzavoa zachar kan betzavoa nekeva. Alright fine, the
משנה or there's these two versions of which is which, but the
משנה is talking about a male and the ברייתא and רבי מאיר
Rabi Meir was adding the female or vice versa. But they're both
the same. I mean they're both, you know, whatever, the same type
of animal. ותניא, vetanya, now, now just so you should be aware
that there's a significant difference, because you don't have to say male
and female of every species, be aware there's a significant difference by
this צבוע tzavoa between male and female, because we teach in a
ברייתא. צבוע זכר, tzavoa zachar, a male צבוע, tzavoa, male hyena let's
say, לאחר שבע שנים נעשה עטלף. le’achar sheva shanim na’aseh atalef. After
seven years it turns into a bat. עטלף לאחר שבע שנים נעשה
ערפד, atalef le’achar sheva shanim na’aseh arpad, and the bat after seven
years turns into an ערפד, arpad, which presumably is another type of
a bat, at least according to what I looked up. ערפד לאחר
שבע שנים, arpad le’achar sheva shanim, and after seven years נעשה קימוש,
na’aseh kimosh, that becomes a type of a thorn bush. וקימוש לאחר
שבע שנים, vekimosh le’achar sheva shanim, after seven years נעשה חוח, na’aseh
choach, that also becomes like a different type of a thorn bush.
So presumably, at least the way the מהרש"א Maharsha says it, is
these are like on the bottom of their chain, like a hyena
is a despised animal. You ever watch Lion King? Was that the
hyenas or the jag—whatever? It was the hyenas. Okay, anyway, bats seem
to be as—I don't know why bats are because I know they're
spooky and they're dark and it's at night or whatever. What?
They live in dark places.
They live in dark places. You know, a thorn bush is obviously
a lowly type of a tree. So anyway, but you can also
understand how this leads to ideas of גלגול gilgul and reincarnation. I
mean the גמרא Gemara is claiming that it actually happens, you know,
to the thing itself, like it's part of its life cycle, but
you know, it sort of converges to like other lowly forms of
animals or of going from animals to birds to trees. Okay, I
don't know what to make of it. Okay, וחוח לאחר שבע שנים,
vechoach le’achar sheva shanim, now this thorn bush after seven years נעשה
שד, na’aseh shed, that becomes a demon. שדרו של אדם, shidro shel
adam, which also plays on the word שד, shed, a man's spine
לאחר שבע שנים, le’achar sheva shanim, after he dies after seven years
נעשה נחש, na’aseh nachash, turns into a snake. Okay, you could sort
of see the visual, right? והני מילי דלא כרע במודים, ve’hani mili
d’lo kara b’modim, that's only if he never bowed during מודים, modim,
because then, you know, because then that's a person that never showed
gratitude to God and therefore, you know, so that's—so the—what?
Someone brought up he should die.
Exactly, תוספות Tosafot brings in the גמרא ברכות Gemara Berachot that you
should bend down like a snake and, you know, get up like
a snake or whatever, so there's all that imagery and obviously it
evokes of course the original snake in גן עדן. Gan Eden. Okay,
and your, you know, and your subjugation to to God and so
on, so there's a lot there. אמר מר רבי מאיר אומר אף
צבוע, amar mar Rabi Meir omer af tzavoa, even the צבוע tzavoa
is included in the list. So let's see if we get to
the משנה here. רבי אליעזר אומר אף נחש, Rabi Eliezer omer af
nachash, even the snake. והנן תנן רבי אליעזר אומר בזמן שהן בני
תרבות אינן מועדין ונחש מועד לעולם, v’hanan tnan Rabi Eliezer omer bizman
shehen bnei tarbut einan muadin venachash muad le’olam, and in our משנה
רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer says domesticated animals even lions are—can be a
תם, tam, but a נחש nachash is always a מועד. And in
the ברייתא he says אף נחש, af nachash, sounds like, one minute,
אף מכלל דרבי אליעזר הוו אינך. af miklal de’Rabi Eliezer havu inach.
Oh, it sounds like he's sort of conceding that the other things
are מועד and he's adding נחש, nachash, whereas in the משנה he's
disagreeing and he's saying those other things are not מועד if at
least if they are if they are domesticated. תני נחש, tani nachash,
so fine, take out the word אף נחש, af nachash, just say
נחש. nachash. Okay, that a נחש nachash is a מועד if it's
domesticated because it's never domesticated but the others are not. אמר שמואל.
amar Shmuel. Why do they think that? I don't know, I want
to move on. אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, let's move on. ארי ברשות
הרבים, ari b’reshut harabim, now we're going to get to this question
of what is דרכו darko or not. A lion in
the major thoroughfare. Someone's lion, you're taking your lion for a walk
in the
street, okay? דוס ואכל פטור. das ve’achal patur. If it basically tramples
and eats, which actually basically he means it eats the prey while
it's still alive. It doesn't kill it first and eat it, it
eats it while it's still alive, then that's a normal way of
eating. That's a שן Shen and therefore it's רשות הרבים, reshut harabim,
so you're פטור patur on שן in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. You
had a right to have your lion in רשות הרבים? reshut harabim?
Presumably. I know, it's bizarre. טרף ואכל חייב. taraf ve’achal chayav. However,
if it kills the animal first and then eats it, that's not
a normal way for it to do. Okay, so that would be
קרן Keren and therefore you would be חייב Chayav in רשות הרבים.
Reshut HaRabim. Would you be חייב Chayav half? Would you be חייב
Chayav full? Right, that gets back if it's קרן Keren. maybe it's
a מועד מתחילתו, Muad mitechilato, but even if it's a מועד מתחילתו,
Muad mitechilato, if it's doing a natural act of eating, it's שן
and it's פטור Patur in רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. If it's doing
something which is an act of violence, which is not a natural
way of its to eat, then it's going to be קרן Keren
and חייב Chayav in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, maybe קרן מועד, Keren
Muad, but קרן. Keren. Okay, and therefore it claims, I don't know
if anybody's watched these nature videos, I didn't research it, but it
claims that lions don't eat their prey while it's still alive, not
after it's dead, I don't know. Is that true? Every time I
see it, it always seems like they kill their prey and then
they eat it. What?
Yeah, they say they die pretty fast after the attack.
The prey? Yeah, so by the time he gets around to eating
it, the prey is dead. And this is claiming that to eat
it after the prey is dead is not the natural thing. I
don't know what to say.
What about the סיפא Seifa of רשות הרבים? Reshut HaRabim? Maybe that's
if it's on a chain?
Oh, I don't know. That's not, well let's take a look. It
doesn't seem to be the continuation. I know, but let's see the
continuation. It doesn't seem to be doing that, saying that, because as
you'll see. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: טרפה ואכלה
חיה, דרסה ואכלה פטור, Terafah ve’achalah chayah, derasah ve’achalah patur, since it's
אורחיה למידרס, orchei lemidras, it's its natural way. הכי נמי כמאן דאכלה
פירות וירקות. Hachi nami keman de'achlah perot veyerakot.
So fine. Lions eat sheep and other animals eat fruit. Exactly. That's
their שן in רשות הרבים פטור. Reshut HaRabim patur. Now טרף, Taraf,
now again, I'm reading רש"י. Rashi רש"י Rashi says the difference between
דרס Daras and טרף Taraf is דרס Daras is the animal's still
alive and טרף Taraf is it's dead. It could mean something else,
it could mean a different way of attacking and killing the animal,
but this is the way רש"י Rashi understands it.
דרס Daras is kind of like just stepping on fruit if you're
another animal.
Yeah, but then it wouldn't call it שן. It would, it's called
a רגל. I know, but I would want to say that there's
a difference between alive and dead, but that's the way רש"י Rashi.
puts it. טרף לאו אורחיה הוא. Taraf lav orchei hu. But to
טרף Taraf and to kill the animal before you eat it, that's
not normal.
ומי אמרת דטרפה לאו אורחיה הוא? והכתיב "אריה טורף בדי גורותיו". Umi
amart detraifah lav orchei hu? Vehaktiv "Aryeh toreif bedei gurotav".
A lion
slashes or whatever for its
young or welps? Is that a young lion? A welp, okay. So
the גמרא says no, בשביל גורותיו. bishvil gurotav. I'm going to read
this like רש"י. No, what it means is, if it's bringing food
back to its young baby lions, it'll kill the prey and bring
it back. But if it's eating it at the spot for itself,
it's going to eat it while it's still alive. Okay, one minute.
The פסוק Pasuk continues: "ומחנק ללביאותיו", u’mechaneik le’leviotav, and it strangles an
animal for its, also for its young lions or no, לביאותיו leviotav
is its female lions, right? Okay, lioness. Okay, בשביל לביאותיו. bishvil leviotav.
Fine, that means if it's bringing back home, it's going to kill
it and bring it back, but to eat on the spot it'll
eat while it's still alive. Doesn't the female do the hunting and
the male mostly? Yeah, okay, anyway, whatever. Okay, and now going on
with the פסוק: Pasuk: "וימלא טרף חוריו", vayemalei teref chorav, and it
will fill its hole like
its cave with
whatever its dwelling place with its with its
what's it called?
טרף, Teref, right, with anyway, with the prey, with whatever it attacks.
So it seems like it kills the stuff and it brings it
back and stores it at home. בשביל חוריו. Bishvil chorav. Yes, that's
to put it in storage, it kills it. Okay, but again, to
eat it on the spot, it'll eat it while it's still alive.
"ומעונותיו טרפה", ume'onotav treifah,
and in its dwelling place again these carcasses. בשביל מעונותיו. Bishvil me’onotav.
Fine, if you want to store it up and put it in
the pantry, you kill it first.
Anyway, but on the spot it'll eat it while it's still alive.
And if it doesn't eat it while it's still alive, it's קרן
and it pays full. והתניא, Vehatanya, but don't we teach in a
ברייתא: וכן חיה שנכנסה לחצר הניזק וטרפה בהמה ואכלה, vechen chayah shenichnesah
lachatzar hanizak vetarfah beheimah ve’achalah, if an animal, presumably including a lion,
went into the חצר הניזק chatzar hanizak and slashed an animal and
ate it, ואכלה בשר, ve’achalah basar, and ate meat, so it's already
בשר, basar, it's dead. משלם נזק שלם, Meshaleim nezek shaleim, pays full.
So it sounds like that is אורחיה orchei and presumably we're talking
even about a lion. הכא במאי עסקינן שטרפה להניח. Hacha bemai askinan
shetarfah lehaniach. Okay, that was a case where it didn't eat it
right away, it's like we said before, it killed it because it
was going to eat it later. So the גמרא says: הא אכלה
קתני. Ha achlah katanei. You can't say it ate it later. It
says it killed it and it ate it on the spot. בשינוייא.
Beshinuyah. It changed its mind. First it killed it and was going
to store it, then it decided to eat it on the spot
ואכלה ve’achalah and then it ate it. So the גמרא says one
minute: ומי ידעינן? Umi yad’inan? How do you know how do you
know that it did it to store it and then it changed
its mind? ועוד דשמואל נמי נימא הכי. Ve’od deShmuel nami neima hachi.
Let's say in the case of שמואל Shmuel where it killed it
and eats it on the spot and you said it wouldn't eat
it after it's dead, maybe it planned to store it and then
changed its mind? So the גמרא says: אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק
מצודדים קתני. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak metzodadim katanei. Fine, you got
to read that ברייתא, cut it in half. שטרפה להניח, Shetarfah lehaniach,
when is it חייב? chayav? If it either killed it, slashed it
for storage and then it didn't eat it, brought it back home,
או דרסה ואכלה, o derasah ve’achalah,
it ate
it while it was
still alive. So again we're insisting
that
it's only going to be
שן when
it's still alive. If it kills it and eats it on the
spot, it's a קרן. משלמת נזק שלם. Meshalamet nezek shaleim. רב יימר
אמר: הכי קאמר שמואל: בארי תרבות. Rav Yeimar amar: hachi ka’amar Shmuel:
be’ari tarbut. When did שמואל *Shmuel* say that these types of attacks
were not natural, this טריפה *treifa* attack to kill it and to
kill it? That's only a domesticated lion. A non-domesticated lion, any type
of attacking and killing and eating is all שן *shen*, which by
the way means it's all going to be exempt in רשות הרבים
*reshut harabim*, which remind us what Michael said is completely bizarre, that
I don't say that I have absolutely no right to bring my
lion in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim*. No, no, no, if it does
a שן *shen* in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* you're going to be
exempt. Okay, that's fine. When did we say that these things are
קרן *keren* and unusual, if it's a domesticated lion? דאמר לה *de'amar
lah*, okay, ואליבא דרבי אליעזר *ve'aliba de'Rabbi Eliezer* דאמר לאו אורחיה *de'amar
lav orchei*. Now Rabbi Eliezer would normally say that you can get
things that are domesticated, certain behaviors will then be not natural, if
you domesticate. Okay, and that's why, you know, a normal lion, everything
is considered אורחיה *orchei*, but if you domesticated it, these acts are
not אורחיה *orchei*. אי הכי אפילו דרסה נמי ליחייב *i haki afilu
derasa nami lechayev*? Okay, but if you domesticated it and now it's
not אורחיה *orchei*, so even to just kill it alive and eat
it alive is לאו אורחיה *lav orchei*. Make up your mind, it's
either all אורחיה *orchei*, it's all not אורחיה *orchei*. אלא דרבינא לאו
אשמואל איתמר אלא אמתניתין *ela de'Ravina lav a'Shmuel itmar ela a'matnitin*. Fine,
what רבינא *Ravina* says it wasn't explaining שמואל *Shmuel*, it was explaining
the משנה *mishna*. כי תניא מתניתין בארי תרבות ואליבא דרבי אליעזר דאמר
לאו אורחיה *ki tanya matnitin be'ari tarbut ve'aliba de'Rabbi Eliezer de'amar lav
orchei*. When did the ברייתא *braita*, what מתניתין *matnitin*, one minute?
Okay. So which
מתניתין *matnitin* is explaining it?
Oh, just the very fact that it says that you pay נזק
שלם *nezek shalem*, oh, the ברייתא *braita*, the ברייתא *braita* that we
said of חיה שנכנסה לחצר הניזק *chaya shenichnesa lachatzar hanizak*. So this
ברייתא *braita* that said a חיה שנכנסה לחצר הניזק *chaya shenichnesa lachatzar
hanizak* pays נזק שלם *nezek shalem*, okay, what did he say? He
said, כי תניא מתניתין *ki tanya matnitin*, when did it say that
when it attacks in חצר הניזק *chatzar hanizak* it pays נזק שלם
*nezek shalem*? בארי תרבות ואליבא דרבי אליעזר דאמר לאו אורחיה *be'ari tarbut
ve'aliba de'Rabbi Eliezer de'amar lav orchei*. Now that seems to be making
an easy ברייתא *braita* difficult. The ברייתא *braita* said you pay נזק
שלם *nezek shalem* because it was דרכה *darkah*. He says no, the
ברייתא *braita* that you pay נזק שלם *nezek shalem* when this lion
attacks and eats is talking about it was a domesticated lion and
you're still paying full. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, why according to
Rabbi Eliezer if it's domesticated are you paying full? You're just making
it complicated. אי הכי חצי נזק בעי לשלומי *i haki chatzi nezek
ba'ei leshallumei*. According to Rabbi Eliezer that you can domesticate it, so
now you should be paying half. דאייעד *de'iyad*,
okay, it was warned three times. So now you get that you
can domesticate it and now go back to being undomesticated. אי הכי
*i haki*, says the גמרא *Gemara*, מאי האי דקתני לה גבי תולדה
דשן *mai hai de'katani lah gabei toldah de'shen*? So then why is
it doing a type of a שן *shen*? If it went through
this process of being domesticated and undomesticated, גבי תולדה דקרן בעי למתנייה
*gabei toldah de'keren ba'ei le'misneiya*. It should have been an example of
קרן *keren*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says קשיא *kashya*. Now by the
way that's fascinating, I would personally say, if I domesticated my lion
and then it lost its, then it reversed the domestication, it would
go back to being שן *shen*. Just because it went through the
process of paying half by being domesticated, now paying full by three
times, how much does that permanently resituate it in the category of
קרן *keren*? It's like this discussion we started with, when something is
לאו אורחיה *lav orchei*, how much does that completely resituate it as
קרן *keren*? But certainly this case, even if it was temporarily קרן
*keren*, I would say once it gets back to being where it
was to begin with, it now should go back to being שן
*shen*. Anyway it's an enforced read of the ברייתא *braita*. The ברייתא
*braita* just simply is not talking about domesticated, it's just a normal
case of שן *shen*. So the גמרא *Gemara* does not end conclusively
about how to deal with שמואל *Shmuel* and I should point out
that the רמב"ם *Rambam* completely ignores שמואל *Shmuel*. Okay. So when the
רמב"ם *Rambam* פוסק *paskens* that an ארי *ari* is מועד *muad* and
this goes back to what we said before also about whether we're
talking about שן *shen* or קרן *keren*, the רמב"ם *Rambam* does not
distinguish רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* and רשות הניזק *reshut hanizak*, the רמב"ם
*Rambam* just says that a lion is מועד *muad* to do all
types of damages, doesn't distinguish between טרף *taraf* and דרס *daras* and
so on. So basically going back to the פשט *peshat* of the
משנה *mishna*, that this is just a sort of a מועד קרן
*muad keren* in all circumstances. One does wonder like again, why when
it's just eating won't it be שן *shen*? But that gets back
to Michael's question. Since when do I have a right to have
my lion in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim*? So maybe I never get
to call anything שן *shen* or רגל *regel* by this. I never
have a right to be bringing it into certain zones. So yeah,
so it's an interesting inconclusive end whether there's types of שן *shen*s
here or whether these are all קרן מועד *keren muad*. What do
you want to say though? רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim* and...